{"test_questions": [[{"question": "CaCO3 contains __________ percent of Ca by weight.", "opta": "40", "optb": "48", "optc": "96", "optd": "12", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Solutions which distil without change in composition are called", "opta": "ideal", "optb": "saturated", "optc": "supersaturated", "optd": "azeotropic", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Gases having same reduced temperatures and reduced pressures", "opta": "deviate from ideal gas behaviour to the same degree.", "optb": "have nearly the same compressibility factor.", "optc": "both (a) and (b).", "optd": "neither (a) nor (b).", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is not a unit of pressure ?", "opta": "Torr", "optb": "Newton/m2", "optc": "Parsec", "optd": "Ata, bar or pascal", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The evaporation of aqueous solution of sugar causes its molarity to", "opta": "decrease. (b)   increase.", "optb": "remain unchanged.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "One Newton is equal to __________ dynes.", "opta": "102", "optb": "103", "optc": "104", "optd": "105", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A very dilute solution is prepared by dissolving 'x1' mole of solute in 'x2' mole of a solvent. The mole fraction of solute is approximately equal to", "opta": "x1/x2", "optb": "x2/x1", "optc": "1 - (x1/x2)", "optd": "1/x2", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An ideal gas can be liquified, because", "opta": "its molecular size is very small.", "optb": "its critical temperature is more than 0\u00b0C.", "optc": "forces operative between its molecules are negligible.", "optd": "it gets solidified directly without becoming liquid.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The rate of material __________ is zero in case of a steady state system.", "opta": "accumulation", "optb": "production", "optc": "input", "optd": "generation", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A metal oxide is reduced by heating it in a stream of hydrogen. After complete reduction, it is found that 3.15 gm of the oxide has yielded 1.05 gm of the metal. It may be inferred that the", "opta": "atomic weight of the metal is 4.", "optb": "equivalent weight of the metal is 4.", "optc": "atomic weight of the metal is 2.", "optd": "equivalent weight of the metal is 8.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Molar heat capacity of water in equilibrium with ice at constant pressure is", "opta": "0", "optb": "\u221e", "optc": "1", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If pH value of a solution is 8, then its pOH value will be", "opta": "6", "optb": "1", "optc": "7", "optd": "10", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The chemical nature of an element is independent of", "opta": "its atomic number.", "optb": "the number of protons or electrons present in it.", "optc": "the number of neutrons present in it.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The heat change for the reaction, C(s) + 2S(s) \u2192 CS2(l), is 104.2 kJ. It represents the heat of", "opta": "formation", "optb": "solution", "optc": "combustion", "optd": "fusion", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A sample of well water contains 140 gm/m3 Ca2+ ions and 345 gm/m3 Na+ ions. The hardness of the sample of water, expressed in terms of equivalent CaCO3 in gm/m3   is (assuming atomic masses of Ca :40, Na : 23, C : 12, O : 16)", "opta": "350", "optb": "485", "optc": "140", "optd": "345", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Assuming that CO2 obeys perfect gas law, calculate the density of CO2 (in kg/m3) at 263\u00b0C and 2 atm.", "opta": "1", "optb": "2", "optc": "3", "optd": "4", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "One micron is equal to", "opta": "10-4 mm", "optb": "10-4 cm", "optc": "10-6 m", "optd": "both(b)&(c)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Heat capacity of air can be approximately expressed as, Cp = 26.693 + 7.365 x10-3 T, where, Cp is in J/mole.K and T is in K. The heat given off by 1 mole of air when cooled at atmospheric pressure from 500\u00b0C to - 100\u00b0C is", "opta": "10.73 kJ", "optb": "16.15 kJ", "optc": "18.11 kJ", "optd": "18.33 kJ", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Gases diffuse faster compared to liquids because of the reason that the liquid molecules", "opta": "are held together by stronger inter-molecular forces.", "optb": "move faster.", "optc": "have no definite shape.", "optd": "are heavier", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Equal masses of CH4 and H2 are mixed in an empty container. The partial pressure of hydrogen in this container expressed as the fraction of total pressure is", "opta": "1/9", "optb": "8/9", "optc": "1/2", "optd": "5/9", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is not a colligative property ?", "opta": "Osmotic pressure", "optb": "Depression of freezing point", "optc": "Lowering of vapor pressure", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Atoms of the same element, but of different masses are called", "opta": "isobars", "optb": "isotones", "optc": "isotopes", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If pH value of an acidic solution is decreased from 5 to 2, then the increase in its hydrogen ion concentration is __________ times.", "opta": "10", "optb": "100", "optc": "1000", "optd": "10000", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Kopp's rule is concerned with the calculation of", "opta": "thermal conductivity.", "optb": "heat capacity.", "optc": "viscosity.", "optd": "surface tension.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Density of carbon dioxide is __________ kg/Nm3.", "opta": "44/22400", "optb": "44/22.4", "optc": "22.4/44", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the wrong statement.", "opta": "The effect of pressure on heat capacity of gases at pressure above one atmosphere and above the critical temperature is negligible.", "optb": "The value of Cp of gases increases with increase in pressure, above atmospheric pressure.", "optc": "The value of Cp at critical temperature and pressure reaches infinity.", "optd": "all (a), (b), and (c).", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In case of a ternery system involving two liquid components and a solute, the ratio of the concentration of the solute in the two phases at equilibrium is called the distribution co-efficient. The distribution co-efficient depends upon the", "opta": "solute concentration", "optb": "temperature", "optc": "both(a) & (b)", "optd": "neither (a) nor (b)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Solution made by dissolving equimolar amounts of different solutes in the same amount of a given solvent will have the", "opta": "same elevation in boiling point.", "optb": "different elevation in boiling point.", "optc": "elevation in boiling point in the ratio of their molecular weights.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "N2 content in a urea sample was found to be only 42%. What is the actual urea content of the sample ? (molecular weight of urea = 60)", "opta": "80%", "optb": "90%", "optc": "95%", "optd": "98%", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Specific gravity on API scale is given by the relation(where, G = specific gravity at 15.5\u00b0C).", "opta": "\u00b0API = 200(G - 1)", "optb": "\u00b0API = (141.5/G) - 131.5", "optc": "\u00b0API = (140/G) - 130", "optd": "\u00b0API = 145 - (145/G)", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S.T.P. corresponds to", "opta": "1 atm. absolute pressure & 15.5\u00b0C.", "optb": "760 mm Hg gauge pressure & 15.5\u00b0C.", "optc": "760 torr & 0\u00b0C.", "optd": "101.325 kPa gauge pressure & 15.5\u00b0C.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "With rise in pressure, the solubility of gases in solvent, at a fixed temperature", "opta": "increases", "optb": "decreases", "optc": "remains unchanged", "optd": "decreases linearly", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the wrong statement.", "opta": "'Reduced temperature' of a substance is the ratio of its existing temperature to its critical temperature, both expressed on celsius scale.", "optb": "'Reduced pressure' is the ratio of the existing pressure of a substance to its critical pressure.", "optc": "'Reduced volume' is the ratio of the existing molal volume of a substance to its critical molal volume.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Vapor pressure of water at 100\u00b0C is about __________ bar.", "opta": "0.1013", "optb": "1.013", "optc": "10.13", "optd": "101.3", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "At  room  temperature,  the  product [H+] [OH-] in a solution is   10-14 moles/litre.   If, [OH-] = 10-6 moles/litre, then the pH of the solution will be", "opta": "6", "optb": "8", "optc": "10", "optd": "12", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A solution is made by dissolving 1 kilo mole of solute in 2000 kg of solvent. The molality of the solution is", "opta": "2", "optb": "1", "optc": "0.5", "optd": "0.5", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Average molecular weight of air is about", "opta": "21", "optb": "29", "optc": "23", "optd": "79", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "6 gms of magnesium (atomic weight = 24), reacts with excess of an acid, the amount of H2 produced will be __________ gm.", "opta": "0.5", "optb": "1", "optc": "3", "optd": "5", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the wrong unit conversion of calorific value.", "opta": "1 kcal/kg = 1.8 BTU/lb = 4.186 kJ/kg.", "optb": "1 BTU/ft3 = 8.9 kcal/m3 = 0.038 MJ/m3.", "optc": "1 BTU/lb = 2.3 kcal/kg.", "optd": "1 kcal/m3 = 0.1124 BTU/ft3.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Increasing the temperature of an aqueous solution will cause decrease in its", "opta": "molality", "optb": "mole fraction", "optc": "weight percent", "optd": "molarity", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The activity co-efficient of a solution, which accounts for the departure of liquid phase from ideal solution behaviour", "opta": "measures the elevation in boiling point.", "optb": "is not dependent on the temperature.", "optc": "is a function of the liquid phase composition.", "optd": "measures the depression in freezing point.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Osmotic pressure of a dilute solution of a non volatile solute in a solvent obeying Raoult's law is proportional to the", "opta": "temperature.", "optb": "volume of solution.", "optc": "moles of non-volatile solute.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In case of an unsaturated vapor-gas mixture, the humid volume increases with increase in the", "opta": "total pressure.", "optb": "absolute humidity at a given temperature.", "optc": "both (a) and (b).", "optd": "neither (a) nor (b).", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is an exothermic reaction ?", "opta": "Conversion of graphite to diamond", "optb": "Decomposition of water", "optc": "Dehydrogenation of ethane to ethylene", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Heat of solution in a system in which both solute and solvent are liquids is termed as", "opta": "heat of solvation.", "optb": "heat of hydration.", "optc": "standard integral heat of solution.", "optd": "heat of mixing.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "1 kgf/cm2  is not equal to", "opta": "1 torr", "optb": "1 bar", "optc": "10000 mm wc", "optd": "100 KPa = 100 000 N/m2", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the wrong statement.", "opta": "Heat capacity of a diatomic gas is higher than that of a monoatomic gas.", "optb": "Equal volumes of Argon and Krypton contain equal number of atoms.", "optc": "Total number of molecules contained in 22.4 litres of hydrogen at NTP is 6.023 x 1023.", "optd": "The binary mixture of a particular com-positidn in both vapor and liquid state is known as an azeotropic mixture", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "On addition of 1 c.c. of dilute hydrochloric acid (1% concentration) to 80 c.c. of a buffer solution of pH = 4, the pH of the solution becomes", "opta": "1", "optb": "8", "optc": "4", "optd": "2", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The weight fraction of methanol in an aqueous solution is 0.64. The mole fraction of methanol XM satisfies", "opta": "XM < 0.5", "optb": "XM = 0.5", "optc": "0.5 < XM < 0.64", "optd": "XM \u2265 0.64", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}]]}